<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anno. IIII. Henrici octaui. These be the statutes established in diuerse Parliamentes for the mistery of ye pewterers of London and concerninge the searche of pewter, brasse, and vntrue beames [and] weightes, [and] for deceiuable hawkers, with diverse other orders [and] redresses to be had in the saide mystery, with the renewinge [and?] confirminge of the same statutes.</title>
            <title>Public General Acts. Selections: Pewterers.</title>
            <author>England and Wales.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1589</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B14599</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 16782</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S100296</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99836141</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99836141</idno>
            <idno type="VID">176333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B14599)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 176333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1315:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anno. IIII. Henrici octaui. These be the statutes established in diuerse Parliamentes for the mistery of ye pewterers of London and concerninge the searche of pewter, brasse, and vntrue beames [and] weightes, [and] for deceiuable hawkers, with diverse other orders [and] redresses to be had in the saide mystery, with the renewinge [and?] confirminge of the same statutes.</title>
                  <title>Public General Acts. Selections: Pewterers.</title>
                  <author>England and Wales.</author>
                  <author>Elyot, Thomas, Maister.</author>
                  <author>Nogey, Thomas.</author>
                  <author>Hawke, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Excudebat Guilielmus How,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Londini :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[not after 1589]]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signed: Thomas Elyot. Maister. Thomas Nogey. Thomas Hawke. Wardens.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Anno quarto Henrici octaui.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from colophon.</note>
                  <note>Publication date from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; title page stained; the bracketed "and" inferred.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Worshipful Company of Pewterers of London.</term>
               <term>Pewterers --  England --  London --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-02</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:176333:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>ANNO. IIII. <hi>Henrici octaui.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>English blazon</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe be the Statutes eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed <hi>in diuerſe Parliamentes for</hi>
               </hi> the miſtery of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pewterers of London, and concerninge the ſearche of pewter, braſſe, and vntrue beames &amp; weightes, &amp; for deceiuable Hawkers, with diuerſe other orders &amp; redreſſes to be had in the ſaide myſtery, with the renewinge and confirminge of the ſame Statutes.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:176333:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:176333:2"/>
            <head>An acte made the fourth yeare of <hi>our Soueraigne Lorde, Kinge Henry <hi>the .viii. concerning Pewterers, and true</hi>
               </hi> weyghts and beames. the .vii. cap.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Oraſmuch as a certaine</hi> Acte was made and ſtabliſhed in the Parliament holden at Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter the .xix. yeare of the raygne of the laſt moſt famous Kinge your Father Henry the .vii. (whome God pardon:) Concerninge <hi>Pewterers</hi> and <hi>Braſiers,</hi> hawkinge and walkinge about the countreyes, and alſo concerning falſe beames, ſcales and weyghtes, with a prouiſion for caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of fine mettal and of perfit goodnes, which acte was made to indure to the nexte Parlya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the tennor wherof inſueth. That where many ſimple and euill diſpoſed perſons of this your Realme of Englande, vſinge the ſayde crafts, daily goe about this your Realme from village, from towne, and from houſe to houſe, aſwell in woods and forreſts as other places, to buy <hi>Pewter</hi> and <hi>Braſſe.</hi> And that know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inge theeues and other pickers that ſteale aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well pewter &amp; braſſe belonginge to your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and vnder your marke, and to the Lords ſpirituall and temporall, as to other your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iectes of this your Realme, bringe ſuch ſtolen veſſels to them in ſuch hid places to ſell, and ſel it for litle or nought, and about they bringe it to priuye places or into corners of Citties or
<pb facs="tcp:176333:3"/> townes, and there ſell much part of it to ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers which carry it ouer the Sea by ſtealth.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſayd perſons ſo goinge about, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe other vſing the ſayd craftes, vſe to make new veſſels and to mixe good mettall and bad togeathers, and make it nought and ſell it for good ſtuffe: where in deed the ſtuffe and met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall therof is not worth the fourth part that it is ſolde for, to the great hurt, deceyt, and loſſe of your ſubiectes.</p>
            <p>Alſo diuers perſons vſinge the ſayd crafts haue deceyuable and falſe beames and ſcales,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> that one of them will ſtand euen with twelue pound weyght at the one ende, againſt a quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of a pound at the other ende, to the ſinguler aduauntage of themſelfe, and to the great de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyte and loſſe of your Subiectes byers and ſellers with them.</p>
            <p>For reformacion of the premiſſes, it would pleaſe your Highneſſe of your moſt habundant grace,<note place="margin">The ordi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>naunce.</note> with the aduiſe of your Lordes ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parlyament aſſembled, and by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame, to enact and ſtabliſh that no perſon nor perſons vſing the ſaid craft of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers and Braſiers, from henceforth ſhall ſell or chaunge any pewter or braſſe, new or olde, at any place or places within this your realme but onely in open Fayres or Markets, or in theyr owne dwelling houſes: but if they be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired by the byers of ſuch wares, vpon paine of forfeyture to our Soueraigne Lorde the Kinge,<note place="margin">Penalt x. pound.</note> for euery ſuch default tenne poundes.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:176333:3"/>
            <p>Alſo by the ſame auctority may be it eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed that no perſon nor perſons of what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicion or degree ſo euer hee or they bee,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> from henceforth within the Cittie of London and Yorke or without, eyther caſte or worke any Pewter veſſels or Braſſe, at any place or pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, within this your Realm: but that it be as good fine mettall as is the pewter and braſſe, caſt and wrought after the perfite goodnes of the ſame within the Cittie of London, and by the ſtatutes of the ſame ought to be, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of forfeyture of all ſuch Pewter and Braſſe ſo caſt and wrought of woorſe Pewter or Braſſe than ought to be wrought in the ſame Citties. The one halfe of euery ſuch forfeyture to be to the vſe of your Highneſſe, and the other halfe to the vſe of the finders therof.</p>
            <p>Prouided alwayes that this forfeyture in no wiſe extend to braſſe or pewter,<note place="margin">Prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> beeinge in the poſſeſſion of any perſon, other than the woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers of the ſame, or ſuch as haue the ſame to ſell, and beeing of the craftes or miſtery. Alſo that it may by the ſame auctority bee enacted and ſtabliſhed that no ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner of perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of what degree or condicion ſoeuer hee or they be,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth make no hollow wares of pewter. That is to ſay, Saltes and Pots that is made of pewter called ley mettall, but that it may bee after the aſſiſe of pewter ley mettal wrought within the Cittie of London. And y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the makers of ſuch wares ſhall marke the ſame with ſeuerall markes of their owne,<note place="margin">Penalt.</note> to the intente that the makers of ſuch wares
<pb facs="tcp:176333:4"/> ſhall auow the ſame wares by them (as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue ſayd) to be wrought.</p>
            <p>And that all and euery ſuch wares not ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently made and wrought, and not marked in forme aboue ſaide, founden in the poſſeſſion of the ſame maker or ſeller, to be forfeyted. And if the ſame ware be ſold,<note place="margin">Penalte.</note> the ſayd maker to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feyt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> value of the ſame ſo vnlawfully wrought and ſolde, the one halfe of the ſaid wares or the value therof to be to the vſe of your Highneſſe, &amp; the other halfe to be to the vſe of the finders or ſearchers of theſame.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Beames and weights.</note>Alſo that it may by the ſame auctority bee enacted and ſtabliſhed, that if any perſon or perſons hereafter vſinge buyinge and ſellinge of pewter or braſſe, that hereafter occupy any deceable or falſe beams or weights of the ſayd wares, that euery ſuch perſon or perſons vſing or occupying ſuch deceiuable &amp; vntrue beames or weightes, to forfeit twenty ſhillinges. The one halfe to the Kinge, and the other halfe to the party that therfore ſhal ſue by action of det. And that in the ſaide action no protection nor eſſoyne ſhall bee allowed. And alſo the ſaide party ſo offendinge ſhall forfeyt his Beame to him that ſhall ſeaſe it. And if the ſaide offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der or offe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ders be not ſufficient to pay the ſaide ſomme or ſommes by them ſo forfeyted, that then it ſhalbe lawfull to the Mayres, Baylifs, or other head Officers of ſuch place or places where any ſuch offenders ſhalbe found, to put them in the Stockes, and them ſo to keepe till the next Market day next adioyninge, and in
<pb facs="tcp:176333:4"/> the Market place to put them in the Pillory al the Market time.<note place="margin">Searche.</note> And furthermore that it bee lawfull by the ſaid auctority, that the <hi>May<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> and <hi>VVardaines</hi> of the ſaid crafte of <hi>Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers</hi> within euery Cittie or Borough of this Realme where ſuch wardaynes are. And where no ſuch wardains are, the head officers or gouernours of the ſame Cittie or Borough to appoint certaine perſonnes moſt experte in knowledge of the ſame, to make ſearch within the ſaid Citties or boroughs where they dwel. And ouer this the Iuſtices of peace, within e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Shire at the generall Seſſyons holden at <hi>Mighelmas</hi> ſhall aſſygne and appointe two certaine perſons hauinge experience therin, to make ſearche in the premiſſes in euery part of the Shire aſwel within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fraunchiſe as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out, ſauing in Citties or boroughs where ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers be appointed by the heads or gouernors of theſame. And that all ſuch vnlawful pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or braſſe, as the ſayde ſearchers ſhall finde, the one halfe to the vſe of your Grace, and the other halfe to the ſearchers. And that in the default of the ſayde <hi>Maiſters</hi> and <hi>VVardaines</hi> of the ſaide occupacions not ſearching in forme as is aforeſaid, and wherby that any ſuch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull mettall is caſt or made, or vnlawfull weightes vſed, that then it ſhalbe lawfull to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny perſon or perſons hauing ſufficient cunning &amp; knowledge in the ſayde occupacions by ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Maires, Bayliffes, or head Officers of the ſaid Citties and Boroughs and townes, to ſearch all the ſaide places, and to put thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:176333:5"/> ſaide auctoritie and acte in execution, in forme aforeſaide. Pleaſe it therfore your Grace and wiſdomes in ſo much as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſaide act is thought good and profitable, that it bee ordained, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted, and eſtabliſhed by the Lordes, ſpiritual and temporall, and the commons in this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Parliament aſſembled, and by the aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the ſame, that the ſaid acte may endure for euer. And ouer that be it enacted by the ſayd auctority,<note place="margin">For true mettall and work manſhip.</note> that if any vntrue or deceiuable mettall or workemanſhip of Tinne or pewter, bee founden either in Platters, Chargers, Diſhes, Sawcers, Potengers, Trenchers, Baſons, Flagons, Bottels, Pottes, Salt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſellers, Goblets, Spoones, Cruets, or Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delſtickes, or in any other ſuch wares of tinne or Pewter, wherſoeuer it bee caſt, made or wrought within this Realme or without, and brought to bee ſolde within the ſame Realme. That then it ſhalbe lawfull to the Maire of the Cittie of London, and the Mayſter and Wardaynes of the crafte of Pewterers of the ſayd Cittie for the time beeing, and their de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties, to haue ſearche of the ſame within the Cittie of London and the Subbarbes of the ſame, and that in all other Citties, Boroughs and Townes where any Wardaines bee or ſhalbe, the Maires, Bayliffes, or head Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Wardaines to haue like auctority.</p>
            <p>And where no wardaines bee, then the head Officers or gouernours of the ſame Citties, Boroughs, and Townes to appoint certaine perſons moſt expert and cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ning in knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:176333:5"/> of the ſame, to make ſearch within y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſayd citties, Boroughs, and Townes where they dwell.</p>
            <p>And if any ſuch new wares wrought of Tin and Pewter as is aforeſayd be found defectiue,<note place="margin">Pewter being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue to be forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> and being in the poſſeſſion of the ſeller, that then the ſame perſon or perſons that putteth any ſuch new wares of pewter to ſale ſhal forfait the ſame wares, the one halfe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of our Soueraigne Lorde the Kinge, and the other halfe to the ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers or finders of the ſame.</p>
            <p>Prouided alway that this act concerning y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiture be not preiudicial nor hurtful to any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons hauinge graunte of our Soueraigne Lord y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> King,<note place="margin">Prouiſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</note> or of any of his noble Progenitors by his letters patents of ſuch forfaiture, but that they &amp; euery of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall haue and enioy theſame according to their former graunts and liberties.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An Acte concerning Pewterers, made</hi> in the xxv. yeare of the reigne of our <hi>Soue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne Lord, Kinge Henry the eyght,</hi> in the ninth Chapter.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N their moſt lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>table wiſe</hi> ſhowen,<note place="margin">Petition.</note> and pitteouſly complayne vnto the Kinges moſt royall Maieſty, and to this moſt highe Courte of Parliamente, the Kings moſt humble poore, &amp; obeyſaunt ſubiects, the Maiſter, wardaines, &amp; pore fellowſhip of the craft &amp; miſtery of Pewterers, as wel of the Citty of London, as of all other places within this Realme of England, that where the ſaid craft or
<pb facs="tcp:176333:6"/> miſtery before this time hath bin one of the beſt handycraftes within this Realme, which hath not only growen &amp; continued by mean of diuerſe good acts &amp; ſtatutes made for the true exerciſe of the ſame, wherof one was made in the .xix. yeare of the Kinges moſt renowmed Father, whoſe ſoule God pardon. And one other was made in the fourth yeare of the Kinges moſte victorious raigne, concerning the crafts of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers &amp; Braſiers, of and for the true makinge, mixting, and ſellinge of good &amp; true pewter, and brazen veſſels. And alſo for exerciſing and vſinge of true weightes and beames to be occupied by the ſellers of any ſuch pewter or brazen veſſels within this Realme, ſo that none of the Kinges Subiectes, nor any other perſon ſhould by any ſale of any falſe mixed brazen and pewter veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell, or any vntrue weightes bee deceiued, as by the ſayd ſtatutes more plainely doth appeare.</p>
               <p>Which good Statutes duely put in execution, hath cauſed the ſayde crafte to encreaſe and mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplye, to the great profite and vtility of a great number of the Kings ſubiects, &amp; the commodity of pewter veſſell much to be had in reputation in all ſtraunge Regions and Countreyes, vntill now of late diuerſe euill diſpoſed perſons, beinge the Kinges Subiectes borne, which haue beene apprentices and brought vp in the exerciſe of the ſaide crafte of pewterers, haue now of late for their ſinguler lucre repaired into ſtraunge regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and countryes, and there do exerciſe the ſaid crafte of Pewterers, teachinge ſtraungers (not
<pb facs="tcp:176333:6"/> onely the cunninge of mixtinge and forginge of all manner of pewter veſſel) but alſo doo teache all thinges belonginge to the ſayde crafte of Pewterers. By meane wherof there is not onely brought (daily into this Realme) out of ſtraunge Regions to bee ſolde, great number of thinges made of pewter vntruely mixted and made of Tinne, wherwith the Kinges ſubiects bee daily deceiued, and the people of ſtraunge countries greatly inſtructed in the cunning of the ſaid craft of pewterers, in ſuch wiſe y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> therby not only a great number &amp; quantity of pewter veſſel, &amp; other thinges of pewter made in diuerſe ſortes and faſhions, amounting to a great value, which was dayly and continually wonte to be caryed &amp; conueyed out of this Realme by Merchants in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſtraung regions and countreyes, and there to be ſolde and vended. Wherby the commodity of Tin made into pewter veſſell, which hath beene had in great eſtimacion, as things very neceſſary and commodious, &amp; the Kinges cuſtomes therby much aduaunced, is now like vtterly to ceaſe and decay, and not to be eſteemed as heretofore hath bin, but alſo the ſaide crafte of Pewterers, which at this day ſetteth and kepeth in woorke and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupacion a great number of people, ſhalbe vtter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vndone. And a great multitude of the Kings naturall Subiectes therby fall into idleneſſe, to the great impoueriſhment of this Realme, if ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy remedy for the redreſſe of the premiſſes be not prouided.</p>
               <p>In tender conſideracion wherof, and for refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb facs="tcp:176333:7"/> of the premiſſes,<note place="margin">Any ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of pewter wrought out of this Realm to be forfai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted.</note> it may pleaſe your high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, by the aſſente of the Lordes ſpirituall and temporal, and the commons in this preſent Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyament aſſembled, and by the aucthority of the ſame, to ordaine and enact, that no perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons hereafter, at any time now inhabitinge, or which hereafter ſhal inhabite within this Realm ſhall buy or otherwiſe take by exchaung for other wares, any wares made, or hereafter to be made out of this Realme of Tin, or mixt with Tin, as Platters,<note place="margin">Search &amp; ſeaſure.</note> Diſhes, Sawcers, Pots, Baſins, Ewers, Flagons, Goblets, Salte, Saltſellers, Spones, or any other thinge made of Tinne or Pewter as aforeſaide, whatſoeuer it bee, vpon payne of forfaiture of the ſame ware, in whoſe handes ſoeuer it may be found or taken: and alſo lawfull money currant in this Realme to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue therof. The one halfe of the ſame forfaiture to be to the vſe of the Kinges highneſſe, and the other halfe to the vſe of the finders of the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Penalte.</note>And furthermore be it enacted, that it ſhall be lawfull to the <hi>Maiſter</hi> and <hi>VVardaines</hi> of the ſaid crafte of <hi>Pewterers,</hi> as well within the Cittie of London, as within euery other Cittie, Borough, &amp; Towne of this Realm where ſuch wardaines bee. And where no ſuch wardaines bee, to the head Officer or gouernour, head Officers or go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours of the ſame Cittie, Borough, or towne for the time beeinge to appointe diuerſe perſons moſt experte in knowledge of the ſame, to make ſearch and ſeaſure, and to take into their handes and poſſeſſion all ſuch wares as hereafter ſhall be brought contrary to the true intent and effect
<pb facs="tcp:176333:7"/> of this preſent Acte, in whoſe ſoeuer handes or poſſeſſion any ſuch ſhalbe found.</p>
               <p>And alſo be it enacted by the auctority aboue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaide,<note place="margin">Pre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tices or iorney me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers borne.</note> that no perſon nor perſons occupyinge the ſayd crafte or occupacion of Pewterers, within this Realme ſhall ſet on worke or retaine in his or their ſeruice any perſon or perſons to be his or their Apprentice, or Iourney man beeing ſtraun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger borne out of this Realme, vpon paine to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fait for euery ſuch Apprentice and Iourneyman tenne poundes ſterlinge.<note place="margin">Straun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers ſhall not work pewter within the realm</note> And that no ſtraunger borne out of this Realme ſhall occupy, exerciſe, or vſe from the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> next comming, the ſaide craft of Pewterers, nor worke any manner of veſſell or other ware aforeſaide to bee made of Tinne or Pewter, within any place or places of this Realme, vpon paine of forfaiture of tenne poundes ſterlinge. And alſo vpon paine of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faiture of the ſame pewter or tinne ſo wrought, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it may be taken or found.</p>
               <p>And alſo be it enacted by aucthority aforeſayd,<note place="margin">Exerciſe beyonde Sea.</note> that no perſon nor perſons beeinge borne within this Realme, occupyinge or exerciſinge the ſayd craft of Pewterers, ſhall at any time hereafter reſorte to any ſtraunge Regions or Countreyes, there to vſe, teache, or exerciſe the ſayde crafte of Pewterers vpon payne to loſe the Priueledge &amp; benefite of an Engliſhman. And if in caſe any of the Kinges Subiectes, at this preſente time beinge dwelling in any ſtraung Countrey or Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and there occupying the ſayd craft of Pew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers doo not repayre into this Realme within three Monethes nexte after requeſt &amp; warninge
<pb facs="tcp:176333:8"/> to him be giuen, by writing ſealed with the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſeale of the Wardaines of the ſaide crafte, within the ſaide Cittie of London, and here in this Realme continually from henceforth dwell &amp; inhabite that then &amp; from henceforth he ſhal be taken &amp; reputed as no Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhal ſtand &amp; be from henceforth out of the Kings protection.</p>
               <p>And foraſmuch as ſundry euil diſpoſed perſons which commonly be called hawkers,<note place="margin">Hawkers</note> by auctho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Kinges letters patentes or placarde, do not only goe about from place to place within this Realme, vſinge buying and ſelling of braſſe and pewter. And by colour and pretence of the ſame Licences and Placardes, vſe vnlawful and deceuable Weyghtes and Beames, but alſo do vſe to ſell both Pewter and Braſſe, which is not good, nor truely, nor lawfully mixt nor wrought, to the great deceit of the Kings true lyege people contrary to the fourme and effect of the ſaid good Act and Statute made in the ſaide fourth yeare of the Kinges moſt noble raigne. Be it therfore enacted by auctority of this preſent Parliament, that all ſuch lycences and placardes heretofore had, made, or graunted to any ſuch perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons contrary to the true meaninge, forme, and effect of this Statute ſhalbe from henceforth by aucthority of this preſente Parlyament clearely voyde and of none effecte. And where as in the ſayd act of Parlyament (concerning the craft of Pewterers &amp; Braſiers) made in the ſaide fourth yeare, for diuerſe cauſes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations in the ſame contayned, among other things it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed that no perſon or perſons vſing the ſayd craft
<pb facs="tcp:176333:8"/> of Pewterers or Braſiers ſhould fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth ſell or chaunge any pewter or braſſe, new or olde, at any place or places within this Realme, but only in open Fayres or Markets, or in their own dwellinge houſes, but if they were deſired by the buyers of ſuch wares, vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> paine of forfaiture for euery ſuch default ten poundes.</p>
               <p>Foraſmuch as the ſame forfaiture is to the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſe of the Kings highneſſe,<note place="margin">Hawkers</note> and that any party ſearching or findinge the ſame is not intituled to haue any benefit therby, it hath not bin knowen that any perſon or perſons haue taken any paine to inſearch or make any inquire therof. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof diuerſe &amp; many euill diſpoſed perſons vſinge bying and ſelling both of Braſſe &amp; Pewter and not regarding the ſayd good act, nor the ſayd penalty, daily goe about from Village to village, Towne and towne, and from houſe to houſe, to ſell ſuch Pewter and Braſſe, which is not good. And alſo vſe deceiuable Weyghtes and Beames as they did before the making of the ſayd acte to the great hurt and deceyt of the Kings true liege people and Subiectes.<note place="margin">Penaltie for haw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers.</note> Wherfore be it enacted by the aucthority aboueſaide, that aſwell the moyte of the ſayd forfeiture of ten poundes limi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in the ſaide eſtatute made in the ſaide fourth yeare, as alſo the moyte of all other forfeytures before expreſſed, and euery of them bee and ſhall be to the vſe of the Kinges highneſſe, his Heyres and Succeſſors, and the other moyte of the ſame forfeytures and euery of them to the vſe of him or them, that ſhall ſeaze, finde or preſent the ſaid forfeytures or any of them, or that ſhall ſue for
<pb facs="tcp:176333:9"/> theſame in any competent Court or Courtes, within this Realme by action of debt, bill, plaint or information, wherin the defendant ſhall in no wiſe be admitted to wage his law, or any protec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion or eſſoyne to any perſon or perſons which ſhalbe impeached to haue offended contrary to the forme and effecte of this Statute, ſhalbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowable. This acte to indure to the laſt day of the next Parlyament.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The annotacions of the confirmacions</hi> and renouacions of the aforeſaide Statutes.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</note>ANd it is to be noted that the ſayd laſt act was renewed in the Parlyament holden at <hi>VVeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> the .viii. day of <hi>Iune,</hi> in the .xxviii. yeare of our ſayd Soueraigne Lorde, to and amonge other actes. And that all clauſes, articles, and prouiſions therin contayned to ſtande in their force and ſtrength, to the laſt day of the next Par<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lyament. And alſo the ſayd act was renewed againe in the Parlyament holden at <hi>VVeſtmin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter</hi> the .xxviii. of <hi>Aprill,</hi> in the .xxxi. yeare of our ſayd Soueraigne Lorde, amongſt other actes, as is aforeſaide. &amp;c.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>An acte concerninge Pewterers made</hi> in the .xxxiii. yeare of the raigne of our Soueraigne <hi>Lorde Kinge Henry the .viij. Chap. iiij.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Recitall of the ſtatute made the xxx. yere.</note>WHere at the Parlyament begun at London the third day of <hi>Nouember,</hi> in the .xxi. yeare
<pb facs="tcp:176333:9"/> of the raigne of the King our Soueraigne Lord, and from thence adiourned to <hi>VVeſtminſter</hi> and there holden, and from that time continued by diuerſe prorogations vnto the .xv. day of <hi>Ianuary</hi> the .xxv. yeare of his moſt noble raigne, it was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained and eſtabliſhed by the aſſent of the Kings Maieſty, his Lords ſpiritual &amp; temporal, and the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mons in the ſaid Parlyament then aſſembled, and by the aucthority of theſame, that no perſon or perſons, from that time than inhabitinge, or which after that time ſhould inhabit within this Realm ſhould buy, or otherwiſe take by exchange for other wares, any manner wares made, or hereafter to be made out of this Realme, of Tin, or mixt with Tin, as Platters, Diſhes, ſawcers, Pots, Baſins, Ewers, Flagons, Goblettes, Saltes, Saltſellers, Spones, or any other thinge made of Tinne or Pewter as aforeſaide, whatſoeuer it were, vpon payne of forfaiture of the ſame wares, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it might be found or taken, &amp; alſo lawfull money currant in this Realme to the full value therof, the one halfe of the ſame forfaiture to be to the vſe of the Kinges highneſſe, and the other halfe to bee to the vſe of the finders of the ſame: And further it was enacted, that it ſhould be lawfull to the <hi>Maiſter and VVardaines</hi> of the <hi>Pewterers,</hi> as well within the Cittie of London, as within euery o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Cittie, Borough, or Towne within this Realme where ſuch wardaines were, &amp; where no ſuch wardaines were, to the head Officer or gouernour, head Officers or gouernours of the ſame Citty, Borough, or towne for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> time being,
<pb facs="tcp:176333:10"/> to appoint diuerſe perſons, moſt expert in know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the ſame, to make ſearche and ſeaſure, and to take into their handes and poſſeſſion all ſuch wares as thereafter ſhould be brought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the true intent and effect of the ſayd act, in whoſe ſoeuer handes or poſſeſſions any ſuch ſhould bee found. And it was alſo enacted by the auctority aboueſaide, that no perſon or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons occupyinge the ſayde crafte or occupacion of <hi>Pewterers</hi> within this Realme ſhould ſet on worke, or retaine in his or their ſeruice any perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or perſons to be his or their Apprentice, or Iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neyman eſtraunger borne out of this Realme, vpon paine to forfait for euery ſuch Apprentice and Iourneyman tenne poundes ſterlinge: And that no ſtrau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger borne out of this Realm ſhould occupy, exerciſe, or vſe, from the feaſt of <hi>Pentecoſt</hi> than next comming, the ſaid craft of Pewterers, nor worke any manner of veſſels or other ware aforeſaide, to bee made of Tin or Pewter, within any place or places of this Realme, vpon paine of forfaiture of tenne poundes ſterlinge: And alſo vpon paine of forfaiture of the ſame pewter or Tin ſo wrought, in whoſe hands ſoeuer it ſhould be found or taken: And it was further enacted by the ſayd aucthority that no perſon or perſons being borne within this Realme, than occupying or exerciſing the ſayd craft of Pewterers, ſhould from thenceforth reſorte into any ſtraunge Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Countreyes, there to vſe, teach, or exerciſe the ſayde craft of Pewterers vpon payne to loſe the Priueledge &amp; benefite of an Engliſhman.</p>
               <p>And if in caſe any of the Kinges Subiectes, at
<pb facs="tcp:176333:10"/> that time beinge dwelling in any ſtraung Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey or Region, &amp; there occupying the ſayd craft of pewterers, did not repaire into this Realm with in three Moneths next after requeſt &amp; warning to him to be giuen, by writinge ſealed with the common ſeale of the Wardaines of the ſaid craft within the ſaide Cittie of London, and here in this Realme continually from thenceforth dwel &amp; inhabite that then &amp; from henceforth he ſhould be reputed &amp; taken as no Engliſhma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſhould ſtand and bee from henceforth out of the Kinges protection.</p>
               <p>And it was than further enacted, that where ſundry euill diſpoſed perſons, which commonly were called hawkers, by aucthority of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings letters patentes or placarde, did not onely goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout from place to place within this Realme, v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing buying and ſelling of braſſe and pewter, and by colour and pretence of the ſame Licences or Placards, did not only vſe vnlawful &amp; deceuable Weyghtes and Beames, but alſo did vſe to ſell both Braſſe and Pewter, which was not good, nor truely or lawfully mixte or wrought, to the great deceite of the Kinges true lyege people con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the fourme and effect of a good and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Act and Statute made in the fourth yere of the Kings ſaid moſt noble raigne, that all ſuch lycences &amp; placardes afore that time had made or graunted to any ſuch perſon or perſons contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the true meaninge, forme, and effect of the ſayd eſtatute, ſhould be from thenceforth by the aucthority of the ſayd Parlyament clearely voyd and of none effecte. And where as in the ſayde
<pb facs="tcp:176333:11"/> acte of Parlyament (concerning the ſaid craft of <hi>Pewterers and Braſiers</hi>) made in the ſaide fourth yeare, for diuerſe cauſes and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſiderations in the ſame act contayned, amongſt other things it was expreſſed, that no perſon or perſons, vſinge the ſayd craft of Pewterers or Braſiers ſhould from henceforth ſell or chaunge any pewter or braſſe, newe or olde, at any place or places within this Realme, but onely in open Fayres or Markets, or in their owne dwellinge houſes, but if they were deſired by the buyers of ſuch wares, vpon paine of forfaiture for euery ſuch defaulte tenne poundes. And ſo than the ſame forfaiture was to the only vſe of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings highneſſe, and the party ſearching or findinge the ſame was not intituled to haue any benefite therby: it was not knowen that any perſon or perſons had taken any paines to inſearch or make any inquire therof. By rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon wherof diuerſe &amp; many euill diſpoſed perſons than vſinge bying and ſelling as well of <hi>Braſſe</hi> as <hi>Pewter,</hi> and not regardinge the ſayd good act, nor the ſayd penalty, went daily about from Village to village, Towne to towne, and from houſe to houſe, to ſel ſuch <hi>Pewter</hi> and <hi>Braſſe,</hi> which was not good, and alſo vſed deceiuable Weightes and Beames, as they did before the makinge of the ſayd act to the great hurt and deceyt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings true liege people and Subiectes. Wherfore it was enacted by the aucthority of the ſaide Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, that aſwell the moytie of the ſayd forfei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ten poundes limited in the ſaide ſtatute made in the ſaid fourth yeare, as alſo the moytie of all other forfeytures and penalties, expreſſed
<pb facs="tcp:176333:11"/> and ſpecified in the ſaid actes, and euery of them ſhould be to the vſe of the Kinges highneſſe, his Heyres and Succeſſors, and the other moytie of theſame forfeytures and penalties and euery of them to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vſe of him, or them that would ſeaze, finde or preſente the ſame forfeytures or any of them, or that would ſue for theſame in any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petent Courte or Courtes within this Realme by action of debt, bill, plaint or information wherin the defendant ſhould in no wiſe bee ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to wage his law, or any protection or eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoyne to any perſon or perſons which ſhould be impeched to haue offended contrary to the forme and effecte of this Statute, ſhould be alowable, as in the ſayd act more plainely appeareth, which act was appointed to indure onely to the ende of the next Parlyament than next followinge, and which act was after renewed in the Parliament holden at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> in the .xxviii. yeare of the raigne of our ſayd Soueraigne Lorde, to indure vntill the ende of the next Parliament than next folowinge: And which act was alſo renewed at the Parliamente holden at <hi>VVeſtminſter,</hi> in the xxxi. and .xxxii. yeares of our ſaide Soueraigne Lordes raigne to indure vntill the laſt day of the nexte Parliament than nexte enſuinge:<note place="margin">Confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macion.</note> Prayen therfore in this preſente Parliamente our ſaide Soueraigne Lordes true &amp; obedient Subiects, the Pewterers of this his ſayde Realme, &amp; other the true commons of the ſame, becauſe theſame acte is beneficiall and neceſſary for the common wealth of this Realme: That it may be enacted by the Kinge our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, the
<pb facs="tcp:176333:12"/> Lordes ſpirituall and temporall, &amp; the commons in the preſent Parliament aſſembled, and by au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of theſame foraſmuch as theſame, acte and euery thing therin contained, is good and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neficiall to the common wealth of this Realme, that all and euery the ſayde actes and ſtatutes, and all and euery, article ſentence and clauſe com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſed in theſame, may from henceforth ſtand &amp; abide in as full ſtrength and effecte for euermore from henceforth to indure, accordinge to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port, tenour and effect of the ſame act &amp; actes, as though the ſaid articles ſentences &amp; clauſes were ſpecially limitted recited or declared in this preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t acte.<note place="margin">VVares made &amp; brought from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Sea.</note> And that no perſon ne perſons from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth buy or take by exchange, or otherwiſe take into or within this Realme, to the intente to ſell any ſuch thinges or wares aboue reherſed, made or to bee made out of this Realme vpon paine of like forfaitures and penalties, as are and were expreſſed in the ſayd ſeuerall actes, theſame pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alties and forfaitures to be leuyed as is afore expreſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Maiſter &amp; VVar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>daines ſhall not be let to ſearche.</note>And that it may be further enacted by aucto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity aforeſayde, that if any perſon or perſons doo vnlawfully withſtand, interrupt, diſturbe, or let the <hi>Maiſter</hi> and <hi>VVardaines,</hi> or their deputies of the ſayd craft of Pewterers for the time beeing, or the head Officer or gouernour, head Officers or gouernours of Citties, Townes &amp; Boroughs within this Realme, wherin no ſuch <hi>Maiſter</hi> and <hi>VVardaines</hi> are or ſhalbe, or any of them in ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ſeaſing, and taking into their handes and poſſeſſions ſuch wares as ſhall happen to bee
<pb facs="tcp:176333:12"/> bought or brought into this Realme contrary to the purport and effect of the ſaide eſtatute, made in the ſayde .xxv. yeare of the raygne of our ſayde Soueraigne Lorde, that then euery ſuch perſon and perſons ſo offendinge, in lettinge diſturbing or withſtanding the ſayd ſeiſure or taking of ſuch wares as is aforeſaide, ſhall loſe and forfayte for euery time ſo dooinge the ſumme of fiue poundes ſterlinge, the one halfe wherof, ſhalbe to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Kings vſe, and the other halfe to him or them that will or ſhall ſue for theſame, by action of debt, writ, bill, plainte, or informacion in any the Kinges Courtes of recorde, in which action or ſuite no Protection, Priuiledge nor wager of law ſhalbe allowed nor admitted.</p>
            </div>
            <closer>
               <hi>God ſaue the Queene.</hi>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Thomas Elyot</hi> Maiſter.</item>
                     <item>
                        <list>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Nogey.</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Thomas Hawke.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list> Wardens.</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>Londini excudebat <hi>Guilielmus How.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
